Preliminary Inventory to the GDR Oral History Project Interviews 1990-1994
Hoover Institution Archives
- Konrad Elmer interview by Thomas Banchoff, December 5, 1991 (Box 10, Tape 22)
  1 photo, CV, 1 cassette and transcript. Narrator is a SPD member, Bundestag
- Rainer Eppelmann interview by Dan Hamilton, November 9, 1991 (Box 10, Tape 23)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000104
  1 photo, 2 CV, 1 cassette and transcript. Narrator is a pastor; co-founder of Initiative Demokratischer Aufbruch (DA), its candidate for Berlin in 1990.
- Rainer Eppelmann interview by Banchoff, December 5, 1991 (Box 10, Tape 24-25)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000105
  2 cassettes and transcript
- Oskar Fischer interview by McAdams, March 9, 1993 (Box 10, Tape 26-27)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000106
  1 photo, CV, 2 cassettes and transcript. Narrator is a party official; Minister of Foreign Affairs.
- Peter Fischer interview by Siena, December 23, 1991 (Box 10, Tape 28-29)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000107
  1 photo, 2 cassettes and transcript. Narrator is an engineer and economist; assistant at the Hochschule für Ökonomie, Berlin; assistant of Sigmund Rothstein, Verbandsprasident der jüdischen Gemeinden in Berlin; friend of Biermann and Irene Runge.
- Peter Florin interview by McAdams, March 10, 1994
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000120_a01, 94066_a_0000121_a01 and 94066_a_0000122_a01
  1 photo, CV, 3 cassettes and transcript. Narrator is a government official; member of SED-ZK; representative of GDR by UN in New York; chairman of UNESCO committee; ambassador to CSSR.
- Hans-Dieter Fritschler and Landolf Scherzer interview by Kaiser, September 7, 1992 (Box 11, Tape 33)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000109
  1 cassette and transcript. Narrators are SED leaders in Thüringen. Also includes 2 newspaper articles (with photos of Fritschler and Scherzer): (1) · Peter Pragal, "Jetzt kocht 'Der Erste' auch mal Kaffee für die Partei," in Berliner Zeitung, May 16-17, 1992, p. 61; and (2) · Landolf Scherzer, "Das letzte Gefecht," in Die Zeit, January 2-5, 1990, pp. 9, 10, 12
- Joachim Gauck interview by Torpey, April 23, 1993 (Box 11, Tape 34-35)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000111
  1 photo, CV, 2 cassettes and transcript. Narrator is Bundesbeauftragter für die Unterlagen des Staatssicherheitsdienstes der ehemaligen DDR; Pastor, co-founder of Neues Forum.
- Lea Große interview by Kaiser, February 13, 1992 (Box 11, Tape 36)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000112
  1 cassette and transcript. Narrator is a communist since 1927 who was sentenced to 5 years in prison in 1935 for communist underground activities; Programmleiter beim Sender "Freies Deutschland" in Moscow, hefredakteurin beim Rundfunk Dresden.
- Gregor Gysi interview by Bortfeldt, July 6, 1993 (Box 11, Tape 37)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000113
  CV, 1 cassette and transcript (corr., pencil marks). Narrator is a lawyer; one of the few to have defended oppositionists; advocate of Neues Forum; Leader of the renewed SED-PDS
- Klaus Gysi interview by Siena, January 3, 1990 (Box 11, Tape 38)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000114
  2 photos, CV, 1 cassette and transcript. Narrator is a government official; Head of the Department of Publishing House Volk und Wissen; minister of Culture; ambassador to Italy; secretary of state for church matters.
- Klaus Gysi interview by Siena, December 28, 1991 (Box 11, Tape 39-40)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000115
- Herbert Häber interview by McAdams, March 19, 1990 (Box 11, Tape 41-42, Box 3)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000116
  2 photos, CV, 2 cassettes and transcript. Narrator is a party official; Member DDR Politbüro.
- Herbert Häber interview by McAdams, March 8, 1993 (Box 11, Tape 43-44)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000117
- Kurt Hager interview by McAdams, December 3, 1990 (Box 11, Tape 45-46)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000118
  1 photo, CV, 2 cassettes and transcript. Narrator is a Government official; leading ideologist; member of the ZK of SED, secretary responsible for the ZK für Kultur und Wissenschaft.
- Kurt Hager interview by McAdams, July 11, 1991 (Box 11, Tape 47-48)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000119
- Kurt Hager interview by Catherine Epstein, August 6, 1993 (Box 12, Tape 49-50)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000120
  2 cassettes and transcript (corr., pencil marks)
- Erich Hahn interview by Bortfeldt, February 28, 1991 (Box 12, Tape 51)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000121
  1 photo, CV, 1 cassette and transcript. Narrator is a Professor of Marxist and Leninist Philosophy; candidate of SED-ZK since 1976.
- Brunhilde and Helmut Hanke interview by K. H. Plagemann, July 22, 1991 (Box 12, Tape 52)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000122
  1 cassette (beginning missing) and transcript. Narrator is Mayor of Potsdam since 1961; member of the Staatsrat.
- Wolfgang Harich interview by McAdams, December 1, 1990 (Box 12, Tape 53-54)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000132
  1 photo, CV, 2 cassettes and transcript. Narrator taught Marxist Philosophy at the Humboldt Univ. until arrested for "Bildung einer konspirativen staatsfeindlichen Gruppe" in 1956; released from prison in 1964; publisher's reader at the Aufbau Verlag.
- Wolfgang Herger interview by Torpey, September 16, 1991 (Box 12, Tape 55)
  Use copy reference number: 84066_a_0000133
  1 photo, CV, 1 cassette (audio quality poor, echo), no transcript. Narrator is a party official; member DDR Politbüro.
- Wolfgang Herger interview by Torpey, January 30, 1992 (Box 12, Tape 56-57)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000134
- Frank-Joachim Herrmann interview by McAdams, March 11, 1994 (Box 12, Tape 58-59, Box 4)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000135
  1 photo, CV, 2 cassettes and transcript. Narrator is a Mitarbeiter des ZK der SED; editor-in-chief of the "Berliner Zeitung".
- Uwe-Jens Heuer interview by Banchoff, November 14, 1991 (Box 12, Tape 60)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000136
  CV, 1 cassette and transcript, 1 election brochure. Narrator is a Professor of law; was advising the ZK in questions concerning Staats-und Wirtschaftsrecht at the Zentralinstitut für sozialistische Wirtschaftsführung.
- Stephan Hilsberg interview by Banchoff, June 14, 1991 (Box 12, Tape 61)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000137
  1 photo, CV, 1 cassette. Narrator is a Computer scientist; co-founder of the SPD (East); member of the Bundestag.
- Gustav Just interview by Torpey, July 14, 1991 (Box 13, Tape 62)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000138
  1 photo, 1 cassette and transcript. Narrator is a Member of Gruppe Harich, SPD member Brandenburger Landtag.
- Gustav Just interview by Torpey, February 1, 1992 (Box 13, Tape 63-64)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000139
  2 cassettes. 1 article: Hanno Kühnert, "Die Schüsse im Leben des Gustav Just," in Die Zeit, Apr. 16, 1993, p. 16.
- Dietmar Keller interview by Banchoff, November 25, 1991 (Box 13, Tape 65)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000140
  1 photo, CV, 1 cassette and transcript. Narrator held Various positions within the Kultur-ministerium; minister of culture in 1989, open to reforms.
- Karl-Heinz Kern interview by McAdams, May 22, 1992 (Box 13, Tape 66-67)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000141
  1 photo, CV, 2 cassettes and transcript. Narrator is a Chemist; diplomat; GDR ambassador to Great Britain.
- Günther Kleiber interview by Zechmeister, November 26, 1992 (Box 13, Tape 68-69)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000142
  CV, 2 cassettes and transcript. Narrator is an Electrical engineer; various party positions linked to the fields of Elektrotechnik, Elektronik, data processing; Stell-vertretender Ministerprasident der DDR; Minister für Allg. Maschinen-, Landmaschinen-und Fahrzeugbau.
- Gerd König interview by McAdams, March 9, 1993 (Box 13, Tape 70-71)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000143
  1 photo, CV, 2 cassettes and transcript. Narrator is a Diplomat; ambassador to the CSSR.
- Ernst Krabatsch interview by Banchoff, March 25, 1992 (Box 13, Tape 72)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000150
  CV, 1 cassette and transcript. Narrator is a Diplomat; member of the GDR delegation to intern. conferences on various occasions.
- Egon Krenz interview by Bortfeldt, May 31, 1990 (Box 13, Tape 73-74)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000151
  CV, 1 cassettes and transcript. Narrator is General secretary and head of Staatsrat after Honecker's retirement; chief executive of the country during the transition period (Oct. 18 - Dec. 3, 1989); expelled from the SED in Jan. 1990.
- Jürgen Kuczynski interview by Bortfeldt, January 10, 1991 (Box 13, Tape 75, Box 5)
  CV, 1 cassette and transcript, 1 note anouncing K's new book: Ein hoffnungsloser Fall von Optimismus. Memoiren 1989-94, Berlin: Aufbau Verlag, 1994. Narrator is an old communist; economist; professor of Economic History at Humboldt Univ., Direktor des Instituts für Geschichte der Wirtschaftswiss. der Akad. der Wissenschaften.
  Access
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000152
- Manfred Lötsch interview by Torpey, February 27, 1991 (Box 13, Tape 76)
  1 photo, 1 cassette (bad audio quality), no transcript. Narrator is a Reform-oriented sociologist at the Acad. of Social Sciences, Berlin.
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000153
- Manfred Lötsch interview by Torpey, January 28, 1992 (Box 13, Tape 77-78)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000154
  2 cassettes (audio OK in the beginning), transcript missing.
- Lothar de Maizière interview by Hamilton, November 12, 1991 (Box 14, Tape 79-81)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000155
  CV, 3 cassettes and transcript. Narrator is a Lawyer; becomes head of the CDU of the DDR in 1989; last Prime Minister of the GDR.
- Lothar de Maizière interview by Bortfeldt, November 4, 1992 (Box 14, Tape 82)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000156
- Moritz Mebel interview by Bortfeldt, February 27, 1991 (Box 14, Tape 83-84)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000157
  CV, 1 photo, 2 cassettes and transcript. Narrator is a Chefarzt für Urologie an der Charité.
- Markus Meckel interview by Banchoff, June 10, 1991 (Box 14, Tape 85)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000158
  1 photo, 2 CV, 1 cassette and transcript. Narrator is a Pastor; co-founder of the East German Social Democratic Party; foreign minister of the DDR (April - August 1990).
- Daniil Efimovich (Melanid) Mel'nikov interview by Sandler, July 1, 1992 (Box 14, Tape 86)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000159
  1 photo, 1 cassette (in Russian) and transcript. Regarding German-Soviet relations. Narrator Worked at TASS and for the SovInformbiuro.
- Hans-J. Misselwitz interview by Bortfeldt, June 3, 1993 (Box 14, Tape 87)
  1 cassette and transcript. Narrator is a Biochemist; pastor; Parlamentarischer Staatssekretar (SPD) beim Außen-ministerium (under de Maizière).
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000160
- Hans Modrow interview by Bortfeldt, March 17, 1993 (Box 14, Tape 88)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000161
  CV, 1 cassette and transcript. Narrator is a Dr. phil. in Wirtschaftswissenschaften; within the SED for democratic reforms; on Nov. 13, 1989, elected head of the DDR- Ministerrat, successor of Stoph; Proposes gradualist unification plan in Feb. 1990.
- Claus Montag interview by McAdams, July 9, 1991 (Box 14, Tape 89)
  1 cassette and transcript. Narrator is Head of Abteilung Außenpolitik der USA des Inst. für internat. Beziehungen an der Akademie für Staats- und Rechtswissen- schaft der DDR. Publications on East-West relations. Botschaftsrat.
- Erwin Müller interview by McAdams, May 21, 1992 (Box 14, Tape 90-91)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000163
  1 photo, 2 cassettes and transcript. Narrator is a Schlosser. Jounalist. Editor-in-chief of " Was und Wie. "
- Harald Neubert interview by McAdams, December 4, 1990 (Box 14, Tape 92)
  2 photos, 1 cassette and transcript. No commercial use without permission. Narrator is a Professor of History. Leiter des Instituts für internationale Arbeiterbewegung an der Akademie für Gesellschaftswissenschaften beim ZK der SED.
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000164
- Erich Nickel interview by McAdams, March 12, 1994 (Box 14, Tape 93-94, Box 6)
  1 photo, 2 cassettes and transcript. Narrator is a Librarian. Historian. Author of Geschichte der Bundesrepublik Deutschland. In the GDR published under the title: Die BRD. Ein Überblick. Emigrated in 1989.
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000165
- Boris Orlov interview by Sandler, June 23, 1992 (Box 14, Tape 95)
  1 photo, 1 cassette (in Russian) and transcript. Narrator is a Historian at the Academy of Sciences in Moscow ( Institut nauchnoi informatsii po obshchestvennym naukam). Special interest: German Social Democrats.
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000166
- Rainer Ortleb interview by Banchoff, December 19, 1991 (Box 15, Tape 96)
  1 photo, 2 CV, 1 cassette and transcript. Narrator is a Mathematician. Since 1968 member of the LDPD, then LDP. Head of the LDP (Feb. 2, 1990).
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000167
- Karl-Ernst Plagemann interview by McAdams, November 17, 1990 (Box 15, Tape 97)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000168
  1 cassette and transcript. Narrator is a Mitarbeiter am Institut für internat. Beziehungen an der Akad. für Staats-und Rechtswissenschaft der DDR, Potsdam-Babelsberg.
- Jens (and Christian in Engl.) Reich interview by Siena, December 28, 1989 (Box 15, Tape 98)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000169
  2 photos, CV, 1 cassette. Side A: Christian (in Engl.), no transcript Jens (in German and Engl.) and transcript, quality ok; Christian (in Engl.), no transcript. Side B: Christian (in Engl.), no transcript. Narrator is a Microbiologist. Co-founder of the protest movement Neues Forum.
- Jens (and Christian in Engl.) Reich interviwe by Siena, December 23, 1991 (Box 15, Tape 99)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000170
- Klaus Reichenbach interview by Banchoff, May 6, 1992 (Box 15, Tape 100)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000171
  CV, 1 cassette and transcript. Narrator is an Engineer. Lawyer. 1990 Landesvorstand der CDU Sachsen. Member of the Volkskammer. GDR minister.
- Otto Reinhold interview by McAdams, March 23, 1990 (Box 15, Tape 101-102)
  1 photo, 2 cassettes and transcript with errata sheet. Narrator is Director of the Academy of Social Sciences [ Akad. für Gesellschaftswissenschaften]
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000172
- Otto Reinhold interview by Bortfeldt, January 29, 1991 (Box 15, Tape 103-104)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000173
- Rolf Reißig interview by McAdams, May 19, 1992 (Box 17, Tape 105-106)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000174
  1 photo, 2 cassettes and transcript with errata sheet. Narrator is a Professor at the Acad. of Social Sciences.
- Irene Runge interview by Siena, December 19, 1991 (Box 15, Tape 107-108)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000175
  2 photos, 2 cassettes and transcript (corr., many pencil marks). Narrator is a Sociologist, anthropologist, journalist.
- Landolf Scherzer (see Fritschler)
  Narrator is a Writer. Author of Der Erste, Köln: Kiepenheuer & Witsch, 1986, an account of Fritschler's political work.
- Hans Schindler interview by McAdams, October 3,1991 (Box 7, Box 15, Tape 109-110)
  1 photo, 2 cassettes and transcript. Narrator is a Dipl. Staatswissenschaftler, Fachrichtung Außenpolitik (Potsdam/Babelsberg). Secretary at the ambassy in Moscow. tellvertretender Botschafter in Bonn (1979-85). 30 Jahre Mitarbeiter Karl Seidels.
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000176
- Karl Schirdewan interview by McAdams, July 9, 1991 (Box 16, Tape 111-113)
  CV, 3 cassettes and transcript. Narrator is an old communist. Member of ZK Politbüro. Together with Wollweber dismissed for opposing Ulbricht. Then Leiter der Staatl. Archivverwaltung der DDR in Potsdam.
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000177
- Gregor Schirmer interview by McAdams, March 7, 1993
  1 photo, CV, 2 cassettes and transcript. Narrator is a Govern. official. Deputy Minister of Education.
- Gerhard Schürer interview by McAdams, July 10, 1991 (Box 16, Tape 116)
  CV, 1 cassette and transcript with errata sheet. Narrator is a Member of ZK. Head of Staatliche Plankommission.
- Karl Seidel interview by McAdams, July 8, 1991 (Box 16, Tape 117)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000203
  CV, 1 cassette and transcript. Narrator is a Diplomat. Botschaftsrat in Moscow. Leiter der Abteilung BRD im Ministerium für Auswärtige Anglegenheiten.
- Wolfgang and Regina (called "Lotte") Templin interview by Torpey, August 29, 1991 (Box 16, Tape 118)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0000204
  1 photo, 1 cassette and transcript. Narrator is Wiss. Mitarbeiter am Zentralinstitut für Philosophie der Akad. der Wissenschaften. Co-founder of Initiative Frieden und Menschenrechte (IFM). 1988 arrested and expelled. 1989 Sprecher der IFM am Runden Tisch. (Lotte: IFM activist. Arrested together with Wolfgang T.)
- Wolfgang and Regina (called "Lotte") Templin interview by Torpey, February 3, 1992 (Box 16, Tape 119-121)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0010873
  3 cassettes and transcript [Lotte on tape #3], no transcript of last cassette (poor audio quality: it is late, W.T. telling jokes.)
- Ferdinand Thun interview by McAdams, March 10, 1993 (Box 16, Tape 122-123, Box 8)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0003441
  1 photo, 2 cassettes and transcript. Narrator is Foreign Ministry chief of protocol
- Wolfgang Ullmann interview by Banchoff, November 12, 1991 (Box 16, Tape 124)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0010881
  1 photo, 2 CV, 1 cassette and transcript. Narrator is Dr. theol, pastor, Dozent für Kirchen-geschichte. Delegate of the movement Demokratie Jetzt to the Round Table. Minister under Modrow.
- Manfred Uschner interview by McAdams, April 10, 1991 (Box 17, Tape 125-126)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0010884
  1 photo, 2 cassettes and transcript. Narrator is Mitglied des Politbüros des ZK der SED. For 14 years Hermann Axen's personal referent.
- Manfred Uschner interview by Zechmeister, March 10, 1993 (Box 17, Tape 127-128)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0010890
- Hans Voss interview by McAdams, May 22, 1992 (Box 17, Tape 129-130)
  1 photo, CV, 2 cassettes and transcript. Narrator is a Diplomat. Consul in Burma and Cambodia, ambassador to Romania and Italy.
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0010897
- Günther Wirth interview by Zechmeister, December 2, 1992 (Box 17, Tape 131-133)
  3 cassettes and transcript, 1 postscriptum by Wirth. Narrator is a Member of the Hauptvorstand der CDU der DDR, editor-in-chief of the journal Standpunkt.
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0010901
- Vincent von Wroblewski interview by Siena, December 17, 1991 (Box 17, Tape 134)
  Use copy reference number: 94066_a_0010908
  1 photo, 1 cassette and transcript. Narrator is a Philosopher. Interpreter (French). Editor of the Rowohlt Sartre-edition.